Finding Aid for the Richard Malcolm Weaver Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Richard Malcolm Weaver Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0495
2.52 linear feet
The Richard M. Weaver Papers include original manuscript materials, correspondence and printed materials deposited by three donors. Mrs. Polly Weaver Beaton, sister of Richard M. Weaver, deposited the greater part of the original manuscript material as well as such items as course notes and some undergraduate materials. Mr. Louis H.T. Dehmlow deposited his personal indexed collection of articles, speeches, drafts, and letters, while the third deposit, containing both printed material and manuscript material, was made by Professor George Core, editor,of the University of Georgia Press.
- Bibliographic materials--correspondence, indices to Weaver’s writings, bibliographies. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Undergraduate materials--essays, article. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Essays--notes and drafts of essays by Richard M. Weaver, holograph and typescript, AcRo. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Essays--notes and drafts of essays by Richard M. Weaver, holograph and typescript, AcRo. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Essays--notes and drafts of essays by Richard M. Weaver, holograph and typescript, AcRo. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Essays--notes and drafts of essays by Richard M. Weaver, holograph and typescript, AcRo. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Essays--So-Un. (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Essays--So-Un. (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Reviews--Typescript drafts of book reviews by Richard H. Weaver. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Reviews--Typescript drafts of book reviews by Richard H. Weaver. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reviews--Typescript drafts of book reviews by Richard H. Weaver. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Speeches--Typescript and holograph drafts, outlines, and notes of speeches given by Richard M. Weaver, Am-Co. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Speeches--Gu-Y. (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Speeches--Gu-Y. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Speeches--Gu-Y. (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Speeches--Gu-Y. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Speeches--Gu-Y. (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Book Manuscript$--Typescript carbon of Foreword to Ideas Have Conseouences. (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Book Hanuscripts--Typescript carbon of Author-Title index of Visions of Order, holograph chapter outline of Visions of Order, correspondence, typescript of General Subject index of Visions of Order (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Book Manuscripts--Holograph and typescript partial rough draft of Visions of Order. (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Book Manuscripts--Typescript draft of Visions of Order, notes from “I. S.“. (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Book Manuscripts--Typescript final draft of Visions of Order, correspondence. (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Book Manuscripts--Typescript final draft of Visions of Order, continued. (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts--Holograph manuscript--“B. Adams”, typescript speech by W. J. Bryan, holograph notes, typescript chapter outlines and prospectus for dissertation, class handouts, holograph class notes, holograph manuscript --“The Conservative Persuasion”, correspondence. (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts--Typescript manuscript--“H. Adams,” holograph manuscript --“Henry Adams,” lists, stationery, “Nine Poems,” notecards and worksheets. (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts--Holograph notes, class outline, photographs. (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts--Poems by Richard M. Weaver (39), typescript carbon of Introduction to Pragmatism (Selections) by William James, typescript manuscript-- “Puritanism,” holograph manuscript-- “Puritanism and Determinism,” “Puritanism and Determinism--Brooks Adams.” (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Miscellaneous Manuscripts--Reading lists, holograph outline-- “Some Contemporary Southern Poets,” staff handout, materials about Symposium on Scientific Attention to Corrununism, Vanderbilt Literary Symposium agenda, clipping. (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Printed Materials--Reprints of essays by Richard M. Weaver, Ac-La. (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Printed Materials--Reprints of essays by Richard M. Weaver, Le-Se. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Printed Haterials--Reprints of essays by Richard M. Weaver, So-Up. (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Printed Materials--Reprints of book reviews by Richard M. Weaver, Am-Ja. (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Printed Materials--Reprints of book reviews by Richard M. Weaver, Je-We. (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Printed Materials--Reprints of speeches by Richard M. Weaver. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Printed Materials--Copies of A Concise Handbook, The Confederate South, 1865-1910; A Study in the Survival of a Mind and a Culture (Ph.d dissertation), Pragmatism (Selections) by William James with introduction by Richard M. Weaver. (Box 6)
- Correspondence Index
  Correspondence is listed alphabetically. The figure in parentheses immediately following each name denotes the total number of letters from that person in the collection; the dates are for the time of the letters. The full name of the writer or recipient of the letter is given whenever possible. The last numbers refer to the box and folder in which each letter is located.
- Incoming Correspondence
  - Burrows, Mrs. Gloria M. (1), 31 January 1962 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Comeau, Brother Alfonso (1), 9 May 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Couch, William T. (2), 22 June 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Couch, William T. (2), 16 November 1953 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Davidson, Donald (1), 25 March 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Davidson, Eugene (1), 23 January 1961 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dehmlow, Louis H.T. (1), 15 April 1963; (to Beatons) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - “I.S.” (1), 14 April 1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Knickerbocker, William (1), 28 April 1942 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Lytle, Andrew (1), 30 October 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Parry, Rev. Stanley (2), 4 November 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Parry, Rev. Stanley (2), 18 November 1960 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Index Of Essays
  - Academic Freedom: The Principle and the Problems., Feb. 1963
    - Typescript carbon and fragment (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Advertising. Date unknown.
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Agrarian in Exile. Appeared in The Sewanee Review, LVIII, (Oct. 1950)
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Agrarianism.
    - Holograph, typescript (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albert Taylor Bledsoe. Appeared in The Sewanee Review, LII (Jan. 1944).
    - Typescript outline, typescript with corrections, holograph notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The American as a Regenerate Being. Appeared in The Southern Review, IV, no. 3 (Summer 1968).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Aspects of the Southern Philosophy. Appeared in The Hopkins Review, V (1952).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Best of Everything. Appeared in The National Review, I (Feb. 1, 1956).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Brainwashing in the High Schools" and Its Critics.
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Causes of War: An Essay in One Sentence.
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Concealed Rhetoric in Scientistic Sociology.
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Conservatism and Libertarianism: The Common Ground. Appeared in The Individualist, IV, no. 4 (May 1960).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Conservatism of Richard M. Weaver. Appeared in New Individualist Review, III, no. 3 (1964).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Contemporary Southern Literature. Appeared in The Texas Quarterly, II, no. 2 (Summer 1959).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Division of the Churches Over Slavery.
    - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Education/ Colleges and Universities. Collier's Year Book, 1954„
    - Typescript, typescript and carbon copy, holograph notes and outline (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Education and the Individual., (July 1959)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hawthorne.
    - Typescript with corrections, holograph notes (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Humanities in a Common Century.
    - Typescript with corrections, holograph outline (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Importance of Cultural Freedom. Appeared in Modern Age, VI, no. 1 (Winter 1961-1962).
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Language is Sermonic, in Dimensions of Rhetorical Scholarship, Roger E. Nebergall, ed. University of Oklahoma, (1963)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lee the Philosopher. Appeared in The Georgia Review, II, no. 3 (Fall 1948).
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Life Without Prejudice. Appeared in Modern Age, I, no. 1 (Summer 1957).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Is Literature Possible for Modern Man?
    - Holograph outline, holograph draft (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Looking for an Argument. Appeared in College English, XIV, no. 4 (Jan. 1953).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lord Acton: The Historian As Thinker. Appeared in Modern Age, V (Winter 1960-1961).
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mass Plutocracy. Appeared in The National Review, IX (Nov. 5, 1960) and in The Individualist, V, no. 1 (Oct. 1960).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Middle of the Road--Where It Leads. Appeared in Human Events, XIII, no. 12 (Mar. 24, 1956).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Middle Way: A Political Meditation. Appeared in The National Review, III (Jan. 19, 1957).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Older Religiousness in the South. Appeared in The Sewanee Review, LI (April 1943).
    - Typescript (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - On Setting the Clock Right. Appeared in The National Review, IV (Oct. 12, 1957).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Parson" Weems.
    - Typescript carbon with corrections, typescript with corrections (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The People of the Excluded Middle.
    - Typescript with corrections, holograph, holograph outline (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Propaganda.
    - Typescript, holograph notes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Randolph and Thoreau.
    - 2 typescripts, 1 with corrections, 1 carbon, holograph notes, holograph fragment (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Realism and the Local Color Interlude. Appeared in The Georgia Review, XXII, no. 3 (Fall 1968).
    - Typescript, holograph (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Regime of the South. Appeared in The National Review, VI (Mar. 14, 1959).
    - Typescript carbon (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Relativism and the Crisis of Our Times., (1959)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Rhetoric of Social Science. Appeared in The Journal of General Education, IV, no. 3, (April 1950)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Roots of the Liberal Complacency. Appeared in The National Review, III (June 8, 1957).
    - Typescript carbon with corrections (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Scholars or Gentlemen? Appeared in College English, VII, no. 2 (Nov. 1945).
    - Reprint (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Social Role of Rhetoric.
    - Holograph (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The South and the American Union. Appeared in The Lasting South, Louis D. Rubin, Jr. and James J. Kilpatrick, eds., (1957)
    - Typescript carbon (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - The South and the Revolution of Nihilism. Appeared in The South Atlantic Quarterly. XLIII, no., 2 (April 1944)
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Southern Chivalry and Total War. Appeared in The Sewanee Review, LIII, (April 1945)
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - The Tennessee Agrarian. Appeared in Shenandoah, III, no. 2, (Summer 1952)
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - To Write the Truth. Appeared in College English, X, no. 1, (Oct. 1948)
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Two Diarists.
    - Typescript, typescript carbon (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Two Orators. Appeared in Modern Age, (Summer-Fall 1970)
    - Typescript, typescript carbon with corrections (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Two Types of American Individualism. Appeared in Modern Age, VII, no. 2 (Spring 1963).
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Ultimate Terms in Contemporary Rhetoric. Appeared in Perspective, XI (1955).
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Uncle Tom's Cabin.
    - Typescript with corrections (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Up From Liberalism. Appeared in Modern Age, III (Winter 1958-1959_.
    - Reprint (Box 6, Folder 1)
Biographical Sketch
March 3, 1910 Born in Asheville, North Carolina. Lived in Weaverville, North Carolina.
1916 Family moved to Lexington, Kentucky.
1927-1932 Attended University of Kentucky. Member of Phi Beta Kappa. Received A.B. degree.
1933-1936 Attended Vanderbilt University. Was a teaching fellow. Received masters in English.
1936-1937 Instructor in English at Alabama Polytechnic Institute.
1937-1940 Acting assistant professor at Texas A & M.
1940-1943 Student at Louisiana State University where he worked with Cleanth Brooks and Robert Penn Warren. Attended summer sessions at the Sorbonne, Harvard University and the University of Virginia.
May 1943 Received Ph.d from Louisiana State University.
1944-1963 Professor of English at the University of Chicago
1948 Wrote Ideas Have Consequences.
1949 Won University of Chicago Quantrell Award for excellence in undergraduate teaching.
1953 Wrote The Ethics of Rhetoric.
1957 Wrote Composition: A Course in Writing and Rhetoric.
1958 Participant in Vanderbilt University Literary Symposium.
1962 Received Young Americans for Freedom award for "service to education and the philosophy of a free society."
April 9, 1963 Died in Chicago, Illinois.
1964 Visions of Order published.
15 March 1991
Richard Weaver correspondence in Special Collections
Cheney, Brainard 0
Curry, Walter Clyde 0
Davidson, Donald 11 (1948-1961)
Lytle, Andrew 0
Mims, Edwin 0
Owsley, Frank 0
Ransom, John Crowe 0
Wilis, Jesse 0
Wills, Ridley 0
The Davidson Papers also contain 2 letters from Davidson to Weaver
Michael Sims